Guide to the William Thompson Dewart Collection of Frank A. Munsey and New York Sun Papers 1833-1944 MS 168
New-York Historical Society
William Thompson Dewart collection of Frank A. Munsey and New York Sun papers
1833-1944
New-York Historical Society
Dewart, William Thompson, 1875-1944
MS 168
30.84 Linear feet (22 document boxes, 37 negative boxes, 13 volumes, 1 oversize folder, and 6 printing plates)
A collection of materials relating to newspaper and magazine publisher Frank Munsey, his general manager William T. Dewart, and their publishing and business activities, especially their work on the New York Sun, purchased by Munsey in 1912. Includes correspondence, photographs, early issues of the Sun and other early New York newspapers, and a complete run of the Sun Rays, an in-house newspaper produced by the Sun's staff.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection includes material donated by Mary Dewart Dooney in 2002, and by Frederick B. Gleason III (grandson of William T. Dewart) in 1985.
Arrangement
This collection is organized in seven series:
Series I: Correspondence and related documents
Series II: Pamphlets and speeches
Series III: Publications
Series IV: Photographs, prints & drawings
Series V: Photograph morgue
Series VI: Scrapbooks
Series VII: Printing plates (replicas)
Biographical / Historical
The New York Sun was the first successful penny daily newspaper in the United States. Founded by printer Benjamin Day in 1833, the Sun was purchased in 1865 by Charles Dana, and within three years reached a circulation of 130,000. An evening edition was added in 1887, and in 1916, the morning Sun and the Evening Sun were sold to publisher Frank A. Munsey.
Munsey was born in Mercer, Maine, in 1854. As a young man with (in his own words) "insatiable ambition," he rose to the position of manager in the Augusta, Maine, telegraph office. Becoming interested in the publishing business, in 1882 he moved to New York City and founded the Golden Argosy, a magazine for boys. After six years, Munsey revamped it into an adult magazine, renamed the Argosy, and now generally regarded as the first "pulp" magazine. In 1889, Munsey started Munsey's Magazine, America's first cheap general-circulation illustrated magazine, which was selling 800,000 copies monthly by 1906. Having made a fortune with his magazines, Munsey began expanding his publishing empire to include newspapers: the Star (1891), the Press (1912), the Sun and the Evening Sun (1916), the Herald and associated papers (1920) and The Globe (1924). In addition to these New York papers, Munsey also owned the Baltimore News, which he purchased in 1908.
After purchasing the Sun papers, Munsey merged the morning edition with his New York Press. In 1920, he closed the morning Sun, and the evening edition was renamed simply The Sun. Munsey bought The Globe and merged it with the Sun in 1924 in order to obtain an Associated Press membership. In addition to his publishing activities, in 1913 Munsey founded the "Munsey Trust Corporation," which was subsequently re-organized as the "Equitable Trust Company" with Munsey as chairman of the board.
Munsey's ceaseless buying, selling and merging of competing publications earned him a reputation as a ruthless entrepreneur, and he is remembered more for his business activities than as an author or editor. However, Munsey also wrote five novels, and during the 1912 presidential campaign became the mouthpiece for "bull-moose" candidate Theodore Roosevelt, co-founding the Progressive Party and writing a series of articles supporting the former president's bid for election.
In December, 1925, Munsey died of a burst appendix, and the paper was purchased by William Thompson Dewart, president and treasurer of the Sun company and the executor of Munsey's estate (Munsey left the bulk of his vast estate, including his newspapers, to the Metropolitan Museum of Art). Dewart's son, Thomas W. Dewart, succeeded him as president and publisher in 1944. In 1950, the Dewart family sold the Sun to the New York World-Telegram.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of correspondence, photographs, drawings, and scrapbooks relating to publisher Frank Munsey, his general manager William T. Dewart, and their publishing and business activities, especially their work on the New York Sun, purchased by Munsey in 1912. The collection also includes bound issues of the Sun and other early New York City newspapers, and a complete run of the Sun Rays, an internal paper published from 1926 to 1947 by New York Sun employees.
The collection is organized into seven series. Series I, Correspondence and related documents, includes business and personal correspondence of Frank Munsey and William Dewart; correspondence and pamphlets relating to Theodore Roosevelt's 1912 presidential campaign; correspondence with other U.S. Presidents; condolence letters, reminiscences and other biographical material solicited by Dewart after Munsey's death; letters and newspaper clippings regarding special issues and publications; and other loose newspaper clippings, including copies of articles by Dewart's sons when they were reporters for the Albany Evening News.
Series II, Pamphlets and speeches, consists primarily of pamphlets, addresses and articles by Frank Munsey relating to advertising, journalism and business. A few speeches by other figures are also included.
Series III, Publications, includes bound copies of the first 18 months of the New York Sun (September, 1833 to December, 1834); special issues of the Sun and other papers; a complete run of the Sun Rays, a paper published by Sun employees reporting on staff weddings and vacations, office developments, and other events of personal and business interest; and a book (The Story of the Sun by Frank M O'Brien) about the history of the paper.
Series IV, Photographs, prints & drawings, includes photographs of Frank Munsey and William Dewart; interior and exterior photographs of the old New York Herald building at Herald Square; a carte-de-visite portrait of William Gordon Bennett; a photograph of Charles Lindbergh receiving an award from Thomas Dewart; and nine drawings (caricatures and cartoons) of or about Munsey.
Series V, Photograph morgue, consists primarily of portraits of prominent figures from the 1930's and 1940's.
Series VI, Scrapbooks, includes three volumes of newspaper clippings relating to Frank Munsey's death, one volume of newspaper clipping regarding William Dewart's subsequent purchase of the Sun, and one volume of newspaper clippings relating to the 100th anniversary edition of the Sun on September 2, 1933. Also included is a Tiffany presentation box containing a memorial to Munsey following his death.
Series VII, Printing plates, includes replica printing plates of an October 1797 issue (the first?) of the Commercial Advertiser, and the Armistice Day issue of the New York Sun.
Americans -- Foreign countries.; Newspaper publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Periodicals -- Publishing.; New York sun (New York, N.Y.); Caricatures.; Letters (correspondence); Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; De Forest, Robert W. (Robert Weeks), 1848-1931; Duffie, Cornelius Roosevelt, 1821-1900; Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923; Munsey, Frank Andrew, 1854-1925; Ridgway, Erman J., 1867-1943; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.)
- Series I: Correspondence and related documents
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes business and personal correspondence as well as newspaper clippings, and is organized into four subseries.
  Subseries I.1, General correspondence, includes correspondence of and between Frank Munsey and William Dewart on personal and business matters. Other correspondents include Erman J. Ridgeway, Richard H. Titherington, Thomas W. Lamont, and Dewart's sons, William Dewart, Jr. and Thomas Dewart. This subseries also includes various news clippings.
  Subseries I.2, Political correspondence, includes letters between Frank Munsey and "bull-moose" candidate Theodore Roosevelt during the 1912 presidential campaign, along with articles and pamphlets in support of Roosevelt's campaign. Also included is correspondence with Presidents Harding, Coolidge and Hoover.
  Subseries I.3, Correspondence relating to special publications, consists primarily of letters (many from prominent figures) acknowledging receipt of various special issues and publications. This subseries also includes loose newspaper clippings relating to special publications.
  Subseries I.4, Correspondence relating to Frank Munsey's illness and death, includes condolence telegrams and letters, and reminiscences solicited by William Dewart from Frank Munsey's associates and friends (arranged alphabetically by the sender's last name). Among the many prominent correspondents are Jules Bache, David Belasco, Richard Nikolaus von Coudenhove-Kalergi, Calvin Coolidge, Chauncey DePew, Thomas Edison, Andrew Mellon, J.P. Morgan, Adolph Ochs, Elihu Root, Charles Schwab, Alfred E. Smith, and numerous others. Also included are notes of interviews with some of Munsey's childhood friends, and biographical newspaper clippings.
  - Subseries I.1: General correspondence
    - Correspondence between Erman J. Ridgeway and Frank Munsey, 1899-1921 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence between Erman J. Ridgeway and Frank Munsey, 1922-1923, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence between Erman J. Ridgeway, Frank Munsey and William Dewart, 1924 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence between Erman J. Ridgeway and Frank Munsey, 1925 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence between Richard H. Titherington, Frank Munsey and Thomas Dewart, 1896-1909, 1913, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence between Thomas W. Lamont, Frank Munsey and William Dewart, 1925-1931 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence of Frank Munsey (business), 1908-1923 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence of Frank Munsey (personal), 1878-1922 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence between Frank Munsey and William Dewart, 1903-1910 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence between Frank Moore and William Dewart, 1911 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence between Frank Munsey and William Dewart, 1912-1922, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence between William Dewart and Robert W. DeForest (President of Metropolitan Museum of Art), 1926-1929 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence of William Dewart, 1908-1938 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence of William Dewart regarding Ella and Robert Pearce, 1933-1935 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence of Thomas W. Dewart and William T. Dewart, Jr. (William Dewart's sons), 1934-1950 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence and articles by William Dewart, Jr. and Thomas Dewart, 1930-1931 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
    - Albany Evening News articles by William Dewart, Jr. and Thomas Dewart (newspaper clippings), 1930-1931 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence and notes regarding business operations and transactions, 1905-1937, 1967 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence regarding advertising, 1937-1949 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
    - Reporters' correspondence and stories, 1916-1934, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
    - New York Press editorials and articles by Frank Munsey (newspaper clippings), 1912-1913 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
    - Washington Times editorials and articles by Frank Munsey (newspaper clippings), 1912-1913 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
    - Articles regarding Frank Munsey's purchase of the New York Herald, New York Evening Telegram, and Paris Herald (newspaper clippings), 1920 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
    - Articles regarding the merger of the New York Sun and New York Herald (newspaper clippings) (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
    - Articles regarding change in name of New York Herald and New York Sun (newspaper clippings), 1920 September - October (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
    - Ephemera (New York Sun roster, reporter's passport, typeface samples, etc.), 1926, 1940, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
  - Subseries I.2: Political correspondence
    - Correspondence between Frank Munsey and Theodore Roosevelt, 1910-1918, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence between Frank Munsey and members of Roosevelt's 1912 Presidential campaign committee (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
    - Frank Munsey articles and pamphlets in support of Theodore Roosevelt's presidential campaign, 1912 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence between Frank Munsey and Woodrow Wilson (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence between Frank Munsey and Warren G. Harding, Calvin Coolidge and Herbert Hoover, 1913-1928 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence between Frank Munsey, Warren G. Harding and Calvin Coolidge (copies), 1920-1925 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence between William Dewart, George Van Slyke, and Franklin T. Roosevelt (regarding map of depression published in the New York Sun), 1934 August (Offsite-box 4, Folder 7)
    - Anti-Roosevelt articles and memoranda, 1935-1936 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence and articles regarding Harry Truman, 1946 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 9)
  - Subseries I.3: Administrative correspondence
    - Letters acknowledging receipt of books by R.H. Davis, 1937-1938 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
    - Letters acknowledging receipt of 100th Anniversary number of the New York Sun, 1933 September (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
    - Letters acknowledging receipt of The Story of the Sun, by Frank M. Obrien, 1928 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
    - Letters acknowledging receipt of The Story of the Sun, by Frank M. Obrien, 1928-1937 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
    - Newspaper clippings regarding The Story of the Sun, by Frank M. Obrien, 1928 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
    - Newspaper clippings regarding The Story of the Sun, by Frank M. Obrien, 1928 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
    - Administrative correspondence regarding The Story of the Sun, by Frank M. Obrien, 1928 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7)
    - Letters acknowledging receipt of The Voice of Business, 1936 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 8)
    - Letters acknowledging receipt of The Voice of Business, 1936 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 9)
    - Letters acknowledging receipt of The Voice of Business, 1936 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10)
    - Letters acknowledging receipt of The Voice of Business, 1936 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1)
    - Letters acknowledging receipt of The Voice of Business, 1936 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 2)
    - Newspaper clippings regarding The Voice of Business, 1936 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 3)
    - Letters acknowledging receipt of The Voice of Business, 1938 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 4)
    - Letters acknowledging receipt of The Voice of Business, 1938 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 5)
    - Letters acknowledging receipt of The Voice of Business, 1938 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 6)
    - Newspaper clippings regarding The Voice of Business, 1938 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 7)
  - Subseries I.4: Correspondence relating to Frank Munsey's illness and death
    - Letters to Frank Munsey during his last illness, 1925 December (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1)
    - Card from flowers sent to Frank Munsey during his last illness, 1925 December (Offsite-box 7, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence regarding Frank Munsey's funeral, 1925 December - 1926 February (Offsite-box 7, Folder 3)
    - Condolence telegrams addressed to William T. Dewart, 1925 December (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4)
    - Condolence letters addressed to William T. Dewart, December 1925 - January 1926 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 5)
    - Condolence letters addressed to William T. Dewart, December 1925 - January 1926 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 6)
    - Condolence letters addressed to William T. Dewart, and copies of Dewart's responses (Offsite-box 7, Folder 7)
    - Condolence letters addressed to William T. Dewart (transcribed copies), 1925-1926 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 8)
    - Letters congratulating William T. Dewart on becoming president of the New York Sun, 1925 December - 1926 January (Offsite-box 7, Folder 9)
    - Reminiscences from Frank Munsey's associates and friends (A-B), 1926 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1)
    - Reminiscences from Frank Munsey's associates and friends (C), 1926 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 2)
    - Reminiscences from Frank Munsey's associates and friends (D), 1926 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 3)
    - Reminiscences from Frank Munsey's associates and friends (E-G), 1926 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 4)
    - Reminiscences from Frank Munsey's associates and friends (H), 1926 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 5)
    - Reminiscences from Frank Munsey's associates and friends (J-L), 1926 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 6)
    - Reminiscences from Frank Munsey's associates and friends (M), 1926 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1)
    - Reminiscences from Frank Munsey's associates and friends (N-)), 1926 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 2)
    - Reminiscences from Frank Munsey's associates and friends (P-R), 1926 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 3)
    - Reminiscences from Frank Munsey's associates and friends (S), 1926 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 4)
    - Reminiscences from Frank Munsey's associates and friends (S-T), 1926 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 5)
    - Reminiscences from Frank Munsey's associates and friends (T-W), 1926 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1)
    - Reminiscences from Frank Munsey's associates and friends (W), 1926 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 2)
    - Reminiscences requested but not received, 1926 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence and editorials responding to unfavorable New York Times article on Frank Munsey by Don Seitz, 1926 March (Offsite-box 10, Folder 3A)
    - Interviews with childhood friends of Frank Munsey, 1927, undated (Offsite-box 10, Folder 4)
    - Manuscript of Frank Munsey: A New England Portrait, by E.P. Mitchell, undated (Offsite-box 10, Folder 5)
    - Newspaper clippings about Frank Munsey, 1925-1926 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 6)
    - Newspaper clippings about Frank Munsey, 1882-1889 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 7)
    - Frank A. Munsey Clippings, 1882-1890 (Offsite-box 64, Folder 1)
      Small, red leather-bound volume embossed "FRANK A. MUNSEY / CLIPPINGS / SEPT. 18, 1882 - DEC. 13, 1890 / PRESENTED TO / WM. T. DEWART / BY / MR. MUNSEY."
      Includes an envelope of "Photostatic copies of checks from World-Telegram to The New York Sun, Inc. January 3, 1950."
    - Frank Munsey will, passport, and map of his estate, 1901 July 10, 1917 March 1 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 8)
    - Resolution memorializing Frank Munsey from the Paris Herald, 1926 January 27 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 9)
- Series II: Pamphlets and speeches
  This series includes pamphlets and speeches by Frank Munsey regarding advertising, journalism and business and political issues. Many are reprints of articles that appeared in Munsey's Magazine.
  For additional pamphlets written in support of Theodore Roosevelt in his 1912 presidential campaign, see Series I, Subseries I.2, Political correspondence.
  - Pamphlets and speeches of Frank Munsey, 1898-1900 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1)
  - Pamphlets and speeches of Frank Munsey, 1902-1922 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 2)
  - "Ideas" of Frank Munsey, 1911-1913 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 3)
  - Speeches of Martin N. Johnson, Stephen B. Elkins and Martin W. Littleton, 1896, 1897, 1911 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 4)
  - Reprints of Munsey's magazine articles, 1900 November - 1912 March, undated (Offsite-box 11, Folder 5)
  - Address and correspondence regarding Munsey Trust Company, 1912-1918 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 6)
  - Address by Frank Munsey to Business Interests of Maryland and Baltimore, 1920 November 30 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 7)
  - Address by Frank Schenider to The Academy of Political Science, 1929 November 22 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 8)
  - The Founding of the Munsey Publishing House by Frank A. Munsey, 1907 December (Offsite-box 11, Folder 9)
  - Copy of a suggested booklet to advertise the Sun and The Story of the Sun, 1928, 1883 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 10)
- Series III: Publications
  This series includes bound volumes of the first 18 months of the Sun, from its first issue on September 3, 1833 through December 31, 1834; bound volumes of other early New York papers; the 100th Anniversary Issue of the Sun and special issues of other papers; a complete run of the Sun Rays, an internal paper published by Sun employees from June 1926 through January 1947; and a book describing the history of the Sun organization.
  - Subseries III.1: Historic newspapers
    - The Sun, 1833 September 3 - December 31 (Offsite-box 61, Volume 1)
    - The Sun, 1833 December - 1834 April 24 (Offsite-box 61, Volume 2)
    - The Sun, 1834 July 14 - December 31 (Offsite-box 61, Volume 3)
    - The Sun, 1834 September 3 - December 31 (Offsite-box 61, Volume 4)
    - The New York Transcript, 1834 July 1 - July 31 (Offsite-box 61, Volume 4)
    - The Man., 1834 November 17 - December 31 (Offsite-box 61, Volume 4)
    - The Free Enquirer, 1832 October 27 -- 1833 October 19 (Offsite-box 61, Volume 5)
    - The Eagle, 1834 September 26 - November 5 (Offsite-box 61, Volume 6)
    - The Jeffersonian, 1834 September 22 - November 15 (Offsite-box 61, Volume 6)
    - The Woman, 1834 October 4 - October 8 (Offsite-box 61, Volume 6)
    - The Man., 1834 October 1 - November 15 (Offsite-box 61, Volume 6)
    - The Constitution, 1834 October 8 - November 8 (Offsite-box 61, Volume 6)
  - Subseries III.2: Special issues and commemorative ephemera
    - The Sun, first issue, 1833 September 3 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 1)
    - 100th Anniversary Issue of the New York Sun, 1933 September 2 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 2)
    - The Times (London), United States Number, 1939 June 8 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 3)
    - The New York Sun, Frank Munsey obituary issue, 1925 December 22 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 4)
    - The Chicago Sun, Volume 1, Number 1, 1941 December 4 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 5)
    - Commemorative version of the New York Sun headlined "Army Leads Navy at Half Time, 10 to 0" (2 copies), 1931 December 12 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 6)
    - Promotional notice for one-year anniversary of the Sunday evening issue of the Baltimore News (Offsite-box 12, Folder 6)
    - Laminated copies (2) of article describing William Dewart gift of James Gordon Bennett Memorial Statue (Minerva and the Bellringers) to New York University, 1928 April 18 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 6)
    - Subscription receipts (framed) (Offsite-box 12A, Folder unknown container)
  - Subseries III.3: The Sun Rays, internal paper published by the Sun Club, social and cooperative organization of New York Sun employees
    - The Sun Rays, Vol. I, 1926 June - December (Offsite-box 13, Folder 1)
    - The Sun Rays, Vol. II, 1927 May - 1928 April (Offsite-box 13, Folder 2)
    - The Sun Rays, Vol. III, 1928 May - 1929 December (Offsite-box 13, Folder 3)
    - The Sun Rays, Vol. IV and V, 1930 January - 1931 April (Offsite-box 13, Folder 4)
    - The Sun Rays, Vol. VI, 1931 May - 1932 April (Offsite-box 13, Folder 5)
    - The Sun Rays, Vol. VII, 1932 May - 1933 April (Offsite-box 13, Folder 6)
    - The Sun Rays, Vol. VIII, 1933 May - 1934 April (Offsite-box 13, Folder 7)
    - The Sun Rays, Vol. IX, 1934 May - 1935 April (Offsite-box 13, Folder 8)
    - The Sun Rays, Vol. X, 1935 May - 1936 June (Offsite-box 13, Folder 9)
    - The Sun Rays, Vol. XI, 1936 July - 1937 May (Offsite-box 13, Folder 10)
    - The Sun Rays, Vol. XII-XIII, 1937 July - 1939 March (Offsite-box 13, Folder 11)
    - The Sun Rays, Vol. XIII-XV, 1939 July - 1940 December (Offsite-box 13, Folder 12)
    - The Sun Rays, Vol. XVI, 1941 January - December (Offsite-box 13, Folder 13)